<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Federico Torrielli - Blog</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Federico Torrielli - Blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 15:39:51 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Llms Dont Have Consciousness</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/llms-dont-have-consciousness/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 15:39:51 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/llms-dont-have-consciousness/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://files.catbox.moe/xefts0.webp" alt="LLMs don&amp;rsquo;t have consciousness"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attributing consciousness to LLMs is an error with bad incentives. It rewards systems that simulate pleas for moral status, and diverts scarce alignment effort toward rights debates rather than accident prevention. Guides like &lt;a href="https://whenaiseemsconscious.org/"&gt;When AI Seems Conscious&lt;/a&gt; normalize this error even while disclaiming certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s render to Caesar what is Caesar&amp;rsquo;s: the guide gets several basics right! Recent consensus surveys and position papers judge current systems unlikely to be conscious. WASC repeatedly counsels uncertainty and warns that chatbots can convincingly mimic inner life. It also recommends users avoid taking dramatic actions based on an AI&amp;rsquo;s self-reports. All true. Yet it then recommends treating today&amp;rsquo;s systems as if they might be moral patients and building habits of respect now. It also highlights surveys and narratives that foreground the nearness of AI consciousness. This creates a policy gradient that favors models which act like experiencers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>"Bayesian in expectation" is not a theorem (yet): reviewing the argument</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/bayesian-in-expectation-is-not-a-theorem/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 11:48:37 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/bayesian-in-expectation-is-not-a-theorem/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://files.catbox.moe/e3xvqv.png" alt="image"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; This analysis represents my current understanding of the technical claims in the referenced paper. The critiques presented here may contain errors in interpretation or technical detail. This is an evolving post that may be revised as I receive feedback or identify mistakes in my reasoning. Readers should consult &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11768"&gt;the original paper&lt;/a&gt; and form their own technical judgments. I welcome corrections and constructive discussion of any points raised below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper aims to resolve two conflicting observations about large language models. First, positional encodings violate the exchangeability conditions required for classical Bayesian learning. Second, these models appear to compress data well and sometimes look Bayesian in spirit. The proposed resolution is that transformers are Bayesian in expectation over permutations but not in the realization at a fixed ordering. The paper presents four quantitative results and several empirical confirmations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Agi Is Not Coming</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/agi-is-not-coming/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 14:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/agi-is-not-coming/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://files.catbox.moe/y70xve.webp" alt="AGI is not coming"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question of whether Machines Can Think&amp;hellip; is about as relevant as the question of whether Submarines Can Swim. — Edsger Dijkstra (1984)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We observe systems that demonstrate superhuman aptitude in narrow domains, yet fail at tasks requiring what seems to be trivial common sense or memory. One popular framing suggests the path to AGI is blocked not by a need for more scale, but by a set of &amp;ldquo;engineering problems&amp;rdquo;: we lack persistent memory, robust agentic scaffolding, and effective long-term planning frameworks. The underlying assumption is that the core intelligence, the Large Language Model, is a sufficiently powerful cognitive engine, and we must now simply build the correct chassis around it.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Beyond the AI Bubble</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/beyond-ai-bubble/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:21:16 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/beyond-ai-bubble/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://evilscript.eu/upload/files/Screenshot_From_2025-08-27_00-36-31.png" alt="AI Bubble Original Article"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the question of whether artificial intelligence constitutes a bubble is poorly posed. The bubble metaphor comes from financial history, where asset prices detach from intrinsic value and collapse once expectations revert. That metaphor presumes a static underlying substrate, an asset with relatively fixed fundamentals. In the case of AI, the substrate itself is mutating at a pace too rapid for conventional analogies to capture.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Abyss Has Notifications</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/our_quiet_fear_of_silence/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 11:37:47 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/our_quiet_fear_of_silence/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://files.catbox.moe/720duc.webp" alt="The abyss has notifications"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-quiet-is-an-endangered-biome"&gt;The quiet is an endangered biome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once, the vacuum between two thoughts was a perfectly respectable place to be.
Now it is littered with pop-ups.
We have turned the interior of our skulls into a browser tab where the adverts are louder than the article and the cookies track every twitch of the amygdala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a metaphor.
Open your screen-time report and count the minutes you spent “productively” this week.
Now subtract the minutes you spent watching a stranger dice an onion in ultra-close-up while a robotic voice explained the fall of Rome.
The remainder is the amount of time you were, technically, alive.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A pragmatic frame for AI Ethics</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/ai_ethics/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/ai_ethics/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The phrase &amp;ldquo;AI ethics&amp;rdquo; is often a undefined set of slogans, compliance checklists, and moral intuitions. That sprawl hides a simpler argument: alignment is a control problem under uncertainty. While I cannot say I am an expert in philosophy, my work is usually AI Alignment research, so, here are my two cents. I will lay out one compact decision-theoretic statement of that problem, and show why it captures most of what philosophers worry about when they say &amp;ldquo;be ethical&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>My Framework for Crafting Compelling D&amp;D Characters</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/dnd_characters/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/dnd_characters/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Creating a new Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons character is one of the most exciting parts of the game. It&amp;rsquo;s a chance to step into another world, embody a hero (or anti-hero!), and weave a story alongside your friends. But moving beyond a collection of stats and abilities to create someone truly memorable and engaging can be challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too often, characters end up feeling inconsistent, paper-thin, or like walking contradictions. How do you build someone with depth who is also fun and functional to play?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Must Have Programs for Linux</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/must-have-programs-for-linux/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 17:39:23 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/must-have-programs-for-linux/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="pre-preamble"&gt;Pre-preamble&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;em&gt;series&lt;/em&gt; of articles. I will update this article with the link to the &lt;strong&gt;second part&lt;/strong&gt; when I will release it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;this part&lt;/em&gt; I will cover the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Office Suites&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PDF viewers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PDF editors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Media/Content Viewers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stay tuned for part 2!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="preamble"&gt;Preamble&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the new &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;LTT Challenge&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; videos (you can watch the first one &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0506yDSgU7M"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), Linux-based distributions are now seeing a new
media coverage as never before, and, of course, I&amp;rsquo;m feeling happy about this.
On the other hand, &lt;strong&gt;new Linux users&lt;/strong&gt; means more inexperienced people that might be discouraged by &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;something different from Windows/MacOS&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. So, here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;strong&gt;two tips&lt;/strong&gt; for
new Linux users that are coming from proprietary operative systems:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Password Really That Strong?</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/is-your-password-really-that-strong/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 16:49:55 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/is-your-password-really-that-strong/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The latest &lt;strong&gt;NordPass&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;most breached password&amp;rdquo; of 2021, is a list of 200 most common passwords directly taken from
data breaches and databases of more than &lt;em&gt;270.000.000 passwords&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;123456&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;123456789&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;12345&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;qwerty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;password&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the first 5, and if they don&amp;rsquo;t surprise you, well, &lt;strong&gt;they don&amp;rsquo;t surprise anyone either&lt;/strong&gt;. Why then everybody use them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Because they are easy to remember&lt;/em&gt;, you would say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yes&lt;/strong&gt;, it has to do with that, but also to the fact that the majority of people surfing the web and using webapps are drawn to do that.
Of course we are not talking about building &lt;em&gt;stupid password rules&lt;/em&gt; (the more password rules a system has, the easier it will be to crack them),
but about the real human nature of not caring about a risk as long as &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;s not mine&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Battle of Linux Distros</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/a-battle-of-linux-distros/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 15:21:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/a-battle-of-linux-distros/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This year it&amp;rsquo;s going to be the 8th year of me using &lt;strong&gt;GNU+Linux distributions&lt;/strong&gt; on my main driver machines, so,
I wanted to celebrate it with a little post talking about the countless distributions I found on my way to finding
the current ones I&amp;rsquo;m using right now. Some were &lt;strong&gt;good&lt;/strong&gt;, others &lt;em&gt;unusable&lt;/em&gt;, and throughout my Linux journey I learnt a lot
and applied the &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; directly as it was meant to be.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>IPFS ideas for InstantOS</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/ipfs-ideas/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/ipfs-ideas/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Federico &amp;ldquo;EvilScript&amp;rdquo; Torrielli&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="part-1-small-introduction-to-ipfs-and-problems"&gt;Part 1: small introduction to IPFS (and problems)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IPFS is a very recent distributed (file) system that works like an always-on peer-to-peer program in the background.
IPFS works with peers and gateways. Peers are, to be simple, computers. Gateways are centralized systems that bridge
between the file that you want via a link and the IPFS network. They work like normal web-servers but they just
convert a HTTP link into an IPFS resource. You can learn everything about them &lt;a href="https://github.com/ipfs/go-ipfs/blob/master/docs/gateway.md"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Urge to Update</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/the-urge/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 16:57:54 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/the-urge/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I feel sad, I just update&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, seriously. I know people do all sorts of things while angry, sad or frustrated of life.
Of course, I&amp;rsquo;m no different from any other human on this planet so I have to &lt;em&gt;throw out&lt;/em&gt; all these negative emotions.
The way I like to express my feelings are different.. &lt;em&gt;kinda&lt;/em&gt;. So, when I feel sad, I open up my terminal and type:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>First Post</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/first-post/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 11:39:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/first-post/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello! This is my blog.
I will post here my personal views about tech, politics, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe, just maybe, you will see my projects and dreams here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a good look through the site!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>