<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Federico Torrielli - Blog</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Federico Torrielli - Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 16:49:55 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Is Your Password Really That Strong?</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/is-your-password-really-that-strong/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 16:49:55 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/is-your-password-really-that-strong/</guid><description>The latest NordPass &amp;ldquo;most breached password&amp;rdquo; of 2021, is a list of 200 most common passwords directly taken from data breaches and databases of more than 270.000.000 passwords:
123456 123456789 12345 qwerty password These are the first 5, and if they don&amp;rsquo;t surprise you, well, they don&amp;rsquo;t surprise anyone either. Why then everybody use them?
Because they are easy to remember, you would say.
Yes, it has to do with that, but also to the fact that the majority of people surfing the web and using webapps are drawn to do that.</description></item><item><title>A Battle of Linux Distros</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/a-battle-of-linux-distros/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 15:21:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/a-battle-of-linux-distros/</guid><description>This year it&amp;rsquo;s going to be the 8th year of me using GNU+Linux distributions on my main driver machines, so, I wanted to celebrate it with a little post talking about the countless distributions I found on my way to finding the current ones I&amp;rsquo;m using right now. Some were good, others unusable, and throughout my Linux journey I learnt a lot and applied the knowledge directly as it was meant to be.</description></item><item><title>IPFS ideas for InstantOS</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/ipfs-ideas/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/ipfs-ideas/</guid><description>by Federico &amp;ldquo;EvilScript&amp;rdquo; Torrielli
Part 1: small introduction to IPFS (and problems) IPFS is a very recent distributed (file) system that works like an always-on peer-to-peer program in the background. IPFS works with peers and gateways. Peers are, to be simple, computers. Gateways are centralized systems that bridge between the file that you want via a link and the IPFS network. They work like normal web-servers but they just convert a HTTP link into an IPFS resource.</description></item><item><title>The Urge to Update</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/the-urge/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 16:57:54 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/the-urge/</guid><description>When I feel sad, I just update
No, seriously. I know people do all sorts of things while angry, sad or frustrated of life. Of course, I&amp;rsquo;m no different from any other human on this planet so I have to throw out all these negative emotions. The way I like to express my feelings are different.. kinda. So, when I feel sad, I open up my terminal and type:</description></item><item><title>First Post</title><link>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/first-post/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 11:39:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://federicotorrielli.github.io/blog/posts/first-post/</guid><description>Hello! This is my blog. I will post here my personal views about tech, politics, etc.
Maybe, just maybe, you will see my projects and dreams here.
Have a good look through the site!</description></item></channel></rss>